Okay. Uh hello everyone. Can you hear me in the back?
in the back? All good. Okay.
All good. Okay. So, uh well, welcome back everyone.
So, uh well, welcome back everyone. Am I uh echoing? All good. Okay. So, um,
Am I uh echoing? All good. Okay. So, um, today I'd like to talk about context
today I'd like to talk about context management for long context agents. And
management for long context agents. And I at first thought about titling this as
I at first thought about titling this as like context management for long context
like context management for long context LLMs because most of the stuff I'm going
LLMs because most of the stuff I'm going to be talking about today is kind of
to be talking about today is kind of more general LLM stuff, but long context
more general LLM stuff, but long context is super super important for when we're
is super super important for when we're working on agents and it's not
working on agents and it's not necessarily covered uh, very well in all
necessarily covered uh, very well in all of the LLM prerequisite classes. So, I'm
of the LLM prerequisite classes. So, I'm going to cover it in a fair amount of
going to cover it in a fair amount of detail today. I'm also going to try to
detail today. I'm also going to try to go through kind of the long context
go through kind of the long context architectures that are used in many of
architectures that are used in many of the kind of state-of-the-art open uh
the kind of state-of-the-art open uh models so you can kind of see the best
models so you can kind of see the best practices that everybody is using in
practices that everybody is using in order to handle a very long context.
So first I'd like to talk a little bit about um how long an agent context can
about um how long an agent context can grow.
grow. So basically the input is quadratic uh
So basically the input is quadratic uh from the uh or the number of token
from the uh or the number of token accesses that you do is quadratic uh
accesses that you do is quadratic uh based on the linear history growth. So
based on the linear history growth. So um if each call uh you make for an agent
um if each call uh you make for an agent takes about you know five tokens and
takes about you know five tokens and let's say you start out with a an
let's say you start out with a an initial system prompt of one token uh
initial system prompt of one token uh you'll get six tokens in the first call
you'll get six tokens in the first call 11 16 uh 21 and 26. you know, this will
11 16 uh 21 and 26. you know, this will increase and increase and increase. Um,
increase and increase and increase. Um, and so by the time you have gotten to
and so by the time you have gotten to the end, you will, if you do things
the end, you will, if you do things completely naively, you will have had to
completely naively, you will have had to process ADK tokens uh for these five
process ADK tokens uh for these five calls. And you know, this can continue
calls. And you know, this can continue for a very long time. I I don't know the
for a very long time. I I don't know the longest anybody has used a single coding
longest anybody has used a single coding agent session or something like that,
agent session or something like that, but I've certainly done them for like
but I've certainly done them for like multiple days uh where I've been working
multiple days uh where I've been working with it for almost the entire day. So
with it for almost the entire day. So you could imagine this could get uh very
you could imagine this could get uh very very large. Um the actual computational
very large. Um the actual computational complexity of this is uh is actually
complexity of this is uh is actually even larger than this. Um
even larger than this. Um well no sorry. So yeah the the
well no sorry. So yeah the the computational complexity is is quadratic
computational complexity is is quadratic here.
here. So why do agent prompts get so long uh
So why do agent prompts get so long uh so quickly? I did a little bit of data
so quickly? I did a little bit of data analysis on uh the composition of
analysis on uh the composition of prompts that I used in um uh 1,500
prompts that I used in um uh 1,500 sessions from our uh coding agent
sessions from our uh coding agent openhands. And
openhands. And each each session was relatively short.
each each session was relatively short. These are not like the long multi-day
These are not like the long multi-day sessions that you do. This is more like
sessions that you do. This is more like solving a single task. But uh each one
solving a single task. But uh each one used about 78,000 tokens on average. Um
used about 78,000 tokens on average. Um 23% of this was a system prompt in all
23% of this was a system prompt in all of the tool descriptions. Uh this is
of the tool descriptions. Uh this is relatively large for a coding agent. I
relatively large for a coding agent. I think our system prompt is somewhere on
think our system prompt is somewhere on the order of like 15,000 to 18,000
the order of like 15,000 to 18,000 tokens because we're very opinionated.
tokens because we're very opinionated. Uh the open ants agent is very
Uh the open ants agent is very opinionated about how people uh do work.
opinionated about how people uh do work. Um these tend to vary from like 8,000 to
Um these tend to vary from like 8,000 to uh 8,000 to 20,000 tokens depending on
uh 8,000 to 20,000 tokens depending on you know how many tools you uh you pull
you know how many tools you uh you pull in and stuff like this. Um separately
in and stuff like this. Um separately from this uh 9% were user messages. So
from this uh 9% were user messages. So this is the user either saying the
this is the user either saying the initial task or following up with uh
initial task or following up with uh additional information after that. 9%
additional information after that. 9% were reasoning traces um and you know
were reasoning traces um and you know where the model is thinking through
where the model is thinking through things. 2% were model replies. Sorry,
things. 2% were model replies. Sorry, this isn't showing on the slide, but 2%
this isn't showing on the slide, but 2% were um the model replying directly to
were um the model replying directly to the user. So, it's spending about um
the user. So, it's spending about um five times as many tokens freezing as it
five times as many tokens freezing as it is spending communicating uh with text
is spending communicating uh with text to the user. And 20% were tool calls. Uh
to the user. And 20% were tool calls. Uh so, you know, uh you know, writing code,
so, you know, uh you know, writing code, uh reading code, that sort of thing. And
uh reading code, that sort of thing. And 37% were tool results. So, this is uh
37% were tool results. So, this is uh you know, getting the result of, you
you know, getting the result of, you know, reading a file or something like
know, reading a file or something like this.
this. So you know each step can uh will
So you know each step can uh will consist of all of these and that tends
consist of all of these and that tends to add up uh very quickly.
So when you're handling this very long context uh there's two big challenges
context uh there's two big challenges here. Uh the first one is capacity and
here. Uh the first one is capacity and so whether your model is able to handle
so whether your model is able to handle this large amount of uh evidence in the
this large amount of uh evidence in the first place and this is a challenge uh
first place and this is a challenge uh because as I'll talk about in a little
because as I'll talk about in a little bit training models to handle very long
bit training models to handle very long context is hard
context is hard um and so in order to manage this you
um and so in order to manage this you need uh things like architecture
need uh things like architecture position encoding training data uh and
position encoding training data uh and uh you also need to be able to evaluate
uh you also need to be able to evaluate whether you're doing a good job of this.
whether you're doing a good job of this. And then the second thing is efficiency
And then the second thing is efficiency uh and whether the system can afford to
uh and whether the system can afford to serve it. And there's a bunch of
serve it. And there's a bunch of techniques to do that as well. And I I
techniques to do that as well. And I I think some people might be taking this
think some people might be taking this for granted if you're just using, you
for granted if you're just using, you know, cloud code or codeex or something
know, cloud code or codeex or something like this, but they're doing some pretty
like this, but they're doing some pretty monumental feats of engineering to take
monumental feats of engineering to take a, you know, multi- trillion parameter
a, you know, multi- trillion parameter model and serve it within seconds uh to
model and serve it within seconds uh to uh over and over and over again for mil
uh over and over and over again for mil I don't know codeex has 25 million
I don't know codeex has 25 million users. So you can imagine uh 25 million
users. So you can imagine uh 25 million daily users hitting it every few seconds
daily users hitting it every few seconds for this huge model. Uh if you want to
for this huge model. Uh if you want to you can calculate in your head how many
you can calculate in your head how many flops per uh per second that might be.
flops per uh per second that might be. It's a lot of flops.
Cool. Um so any questions or things? Probably pretty straightforward I guess.
Probably pretty straightforward I guess. Okay. So uh let's go into inference. And
Okay. So uh let's go into inference. And so in order to make this happen uh the
so in order to make this happen uh the you basically need to be able to um
you basically need to be able to um calculate uh prefill and decoding. So uh
calculate uh prefill and decoding. So uh calculate your inputs and your outputs
calculate your inputs and your outputs at each step. And this uh you know I'm
at each step. And this uh you know I'm sure everybody has done in your previous
sure everybody has done in your previous classes uh for generating from uh you
classes uh for generating from uh you know a language model. some things you
know a language model. some things you may or may not have thought about in
may or may not have thought about in your previous classes. If you took how
your previous classes. If you took how many people took like uh language model
many people took like uh language model systems or deep learning systems or
systems or deep learning systems or something like that actually more than I
something like that actually more than I thought. So if you took the systems
thought. So if you took the systems course you you probably handled this. Um
course you you probably handled this. Um but other things you need to think about
but other things you need to think about are how do you schedule uh multiple
are how do you schedule uh multiple concurrent queries? Um and also how do
concurrent queries? Um and also how do you save the results in the KV cache uh
you save the results in the KV cache uh so you can reuse them and not have to
so you can reuse them and not have to reuse them over and over again. uh not
reuse them over and over again. uh not have to calculate over and over again.
have to calculate over and over again. So going into a bit more detail here, um
So going into a bit more detail here, um we have a few phrase uh phases in
we have a few phrase uh phases in inference. The first one is called
inference. The first one is called prefill. Um you could also call it
prefill. Um you could also call it encoding. Um but I think pre prefill is
encoding. Um but I think pre prefill is kind of the like preferred term of art
kind of the like preferred term of art nowadays. And so you take in all of your
nowadays. And so you take in all of your input tokens uh that you don't need to
input tokens uh that you don't need to generate and uh you generate the key and
generate and uh you generate the key and value pairs uh from each of them. And
value pairs uh from each of them. And then uh when you're decoding you
then uh when you're decoding you basically uh take the prompt uh and key
basically uh take the prompt uh and key value pairs um generate an output and
value pairs um generate an output and append uh the key value pair that you
append uh the key value pair that you get from the output. So um you do this
get from the output. So um you do this kind of incrementally whereas this can
kind of incrementally whereas this can be done in a batched sequence.
And so uh when we think about this as a serving system, there's a bunch of ways
serving system, there's a bunch of ways we quantify how good a serving system
we quantify how good a serving system is. Uh the first one is time to first
is. Uh the first one is time to first token. So this is how long you need to
token. So this is how long you need to start um you need to wait between when
start um you need to wait between when you start uh
you start uh entering a query and when you start
entering a query and when you start seeing the first output. And so like I'm
seeing the first output. And so like I'm sure everybody you know who uses chat
sure everybody you know who uses chat GPT or something like that uh you put in
GPT or something like that uh you put in a long output you notice it takes longer
a long output you notice it takes longer to start getting a response than if you
to start getting a response than if you put in sorry put in a long input you see
put in sorry put in a long input you see it takes longer to start getting a
it takes longer to start getting a response than if you put in a short
response than if you put in a short input and that's like your TTFT is
input and that's like your TTFT is higher. Uh then uh your time per output
higher. Uh then uh your time per output token is the uh time like the amount of
token is the uh time like the amount of time it takes uh between generating each
time it takes uh between generating each token. And if you go to a website like
token. And if you go to a website like open router
um t typically uh here this will be your
t typically uh here this will be your time per output token there I am pretty
time per output token there I am pretty sure they're not counting prefill here
sure they're not counting prefill here and it's just like the time between uh
and it's just like the time between uh each of the tokens that might be a
each of the tokens that might be a little bit small with the black
little bit small with the black background but you can see that um for
background but you can see that um for GLM 5.2 to uh you have like 63, 48, uh
GLM 5.2 to uh you have like 63, 48, uh 24, uh that sort of thing. And you know,
24, uh that sort of thing. And you know, some providers are drastically better
some providers are drastically better than others. Like this provider,
than others. Like this provider, not to pick on Mistl, but they're
not to pick on Mistl, but they're getting, you know, three three tokens
getting, you know, three three tokens per second and then these other ones
per second and then these other ones like Parasel and Coreweave are getting,
like Parasel and Coreweave are getting, you know, hundreds of tokens per second.
you know, hundreds of tokens per second. So um so basically uh you know this
So um so basically uh you know this makes a huge difference in your
makes a huge difference in your experience using um uh using agents. Uh
experience using um uh using agents. Uh one other interesting thing is um
one other interesting thing is um there's different ways people can use
there's different ways people can use agents. And so in some cases you might
agents. And so in some cases you might really hear about this. So like let's
really hear about this. So like let's say you're working together um with a an
say you're working together um with a an agent on a interactive task in your
agent on a interactive task in your favorite coding CLI. you may really
favorite coding CLI. you may really really care about, you know, TTFT and
really care about, you know, TTFT and Tapot. Um, if you're running an agent in
Tapot. Um, if you're running an agent in the background to do some background
the background to do some background tasks that run overnight, you might not
tasks that run overnight, you might not care at all. Um, and there's trade-offs
care at all. Um, and there's trade-offs between them, between like throughput
between them, between like throughput and cost and how fast uh you can get the
and cost and how fast uh you can get the the tokens. And like I you know also um
the tokens. And like I you know also um serve coding agents uh with my company
serve coding agents uh with my company and when I talk to providers they'll
and when I talk to providers they'll often often ask which do you care about
often often ask which do you care about more so we can optimize the system uh
more so we can optimize the system uh for the one you care about more and so
for the one you care about more and so um there's uh there's ways you can do
um there's uh there's ways you can do that and I'll I'll talk about those too.
Cool. Um yeah so sorry just to finish the
Um yeah so sorry just to finish the slide. So throughput is um the completed
slide. So throughput is um the completed tokens or requests divided by the wall
tokens or requests divided by the wall clock time. So this is kind of seen
clock time. So this is kind of seen usually on a more holistic level over
usually on a more holistic level over the whole system. And then uh the cost
the whole system. And then uh the cost is you know how much it costs.
is you know how much it costs. So as a refresher um I I hopefully
So as a refresher um I I hopefully everybody should know this already. Um
everybody should know this already. Um but you have uh the
but you have uh the uh query key and value calculation in uh
uh query key and value calculation in uh typical attention and this is uh so you
typical attention and this is uh so you have this here and then you take the
have this here and then you take the softmax um divide it by this. You might
softmax um divide it by this. You might have some sort of uh you know positional
have some sort of uh you know positional uh bias and then you calculate your
uh bias and then you calculate your output and typical full attention uh
output and typical full attention uh looks uh like this. you mask all the
looks uh like this. you mask all the previous tokens and and or you consider
previous tokens and and or you consider all the current tokens and you mask all
all the current tokens and you mask all the um the future tokens.
the um the future tokens. Um so this is of course very expensive
Um so this is of course very expensive because it's quadratic in the sequence
because it's quadratic in the sequence length. Uh and so a lot of the stuff I'm
length. Uh and so a lot of the stuff I'm going to be talking about today is about
going to be talking about today is about how to fix that.
how to fix that. Um so this is on the efficiency side and
Um so this is on the efficiency side and then on the effectiveness side just
then on the effectiveness side just because you have a model or just because
because you have a model or just because you have a serving system that can take
you have a serving system that can take in you know a million tokens doesn't
in you know a million tokens doesn't necessarily mean that you can use that a
necessarily mean that you can use that a million tokens effectively and
million tokens effectively and um this is a very like old school
um this is a very like old school example of this I guess this is a needle
example of this I guess this is a needle in the haststack evaluation how many
in the haststack evaluation how many people have seen this figure for
people have seen this figure for maybe some but not not that many. Okay,
maybe some but not not that many. Okay, so to explain what this looks like,
so to explain what this looks like, basically what this is saying is um it's
basically what this is saying is um it's a very weird evaluation. Basically, they
a very weird evaluation. Basically, they um they took a whole bunch of Paul
um they took a whole bunch of Paul Graham essays uh by the like famous
Graham essays uh by the like famous entrepreneur and head of Y Combinator
entrepreneur and head of Y Combinator Paul Graham and they stuck in uh
Paul Graham and they stuck in uh something about like the best place in
something about like the best place in San Francisco to eat a sandwich is
San Francisco to eat a sandwich is something or other and then they ask a
something or other and then they ask a question where's the best place in San
question where's the best place in San Francisco to eat a sandwich and then the
Francisco to eat a sandwich and then the language model has to answer that
language model has to answer that correctly. um and they made the context
correctly. um and they made the context longer and longer and longer and then
longer and longer and longer and then they evaluate uh models with the longer
they evaluate uh models with the longer context and eventually the weaker models
context and eventually the weaker models start getting worse at these very very
start getting worse at these very very long contexts and there's a bunch of
long contexts and there's a bunch of examples of things like this. Um ruler
examples of things like this. Um ruler and helmet are kind of the the common
and helmet are kind of the the common benchmarks that people use here. Um but
benchmarks that people use here. Um but basically uh the long the summary is
basically uh the long the summary is that if you have very long context your
that if you have very long context your models might start getting worse at
models might start getting worse at processing them.
processing them. So has anybody noticed this when you've
So has anybody noticed this when you've used a coding agent for a long time like
used a coding agent for a long time like are there common
are there common or used any agent for a long time are
or used any agent for a long time are there common like failure cases that you
there common like failure cases that you see?
see? What what kind of things what kind of
What what kind of things what kind of things have bothered you?
things have bothered you? Anybody?
>> Yeah. >> Forget the previous context.
>> Forget the previous context. >> Yeah. Forgets the previous context. Did
>> Yeah. Forgets the previous context. Did that cause any like problems for you?
with me telling it not to do something in the middle of the conversation and
in the middle of the conversation and then it goes and does it. Um there there
then it goes and does it. Um there there was a really bad example uh where I
was a really bad example uh where I think actually Daniel talked about it
think actually Daniel talked about it here where the person had said do not
here where the person had said do not delete this and then it went and deleted
delete this and then it went and deleted it anyway because it had forgotten the
it anyway because it had forgotten the context. So yeah, this can be a really
context. So yeah, this can be a really big problem in agentic settings because
big problem in agentic settings because you know the user is giving these
you know the user is giving these incremental instructions. So
incremental instructions. So so I'm going to be talking about several
so I'm going to be talking about several different things. I'm going to be
different things. I'm going to be talking about architecture. I'm going to
talking about architecture. I'm going to be talking about training inference and
be talking about training inference and compaction. So going first into
compaction. So going first into architecture. Um this is both about
architecture. Um this is both about efficiency and accuracy.
efficiency and accuracy. And so as I mentioned standard attention
And so as I mentioned standard attention is global. So it makes pairwise
is global. So it makes pairwise comparisons across uh all of the tokens
comparisons across uh all of the tokens here. And um the problem with this is uh
here. And um the problem with this is uh like this is quadratic obviously. And
like this is quadratic obviously. And does anyone know the like standard
does anyone know the like standard length of the of models nowadays of
length of the of models nowadays of these uh of like state-of-the-art
these uh of like state-of-the-art language models?
language models? >> 256 to a million.
>> 256 to a million. >> 256 to a million. Yeah. And I I'd say
>> 256 to a million. Yeah. And I I'd say most people are aiming for a million now
most people are aiming for a million now because they don't want to be the, you
because they don't want to be the, you know, the model that has 256 when
know, the model that has 256 when everyone else has a million. So very
everyone else has a million. So very quick math in your head, how many
quick math in your head, how many pairwise comparisons is that?
pairwise comparisons is that? >> 10 12
>> 10 12 >> 10 10^ the 12 or in English.
>> 10 10^ the 12 or in English. >> A trillion. Yeah, that's a trillion.
>> A trillion. Yeah, that's a trillion. That's a trillion comparisons every
That's a trillion comparisons every time. uh like when you're uh generating
time. uh like when you're uh generating a sequence of a million long and each
a sequence of a million long and each comparison uh requires you to multiply
comparison uh requires you to multiply large vectors by each other over and
large vectors by each other over and over and over again. So you're starting
over and over again. So you're starting to get up into the you know 10 to the
to get up into the you know 10 to the I guess it'd probably be 10 to the 20ish
I guess it'd probably be 10 to the 20ish uh which is a lot that that's a lot of
uh which is a lot that that's a lot of compute um for a single sequence.
compute um for a single sequence. So um there there's ways that people
So um there there's ways that people solve this and basically almost all of
solve this and basically almost all of them fall into the category of taking
them fall into the category of taking this quadratic computation and putting
this quadratic computation and putting some sort of constant limit on the
some sort of constant limit on the number of comparisons that are made uh
number of comparisons that are made uh at each time step. And that brings your
at each time step. And that brings your uh n squared down to owl where I I wrote
uh n squared down to owl where I I wrote w for window but it doesn't necessarily
w for window but it doesn't necessarily need to be a window. It just needs to be
need to be a window. It just needs to be the cap on the number of comparisons
the cap on the number of comparisons that you're making.
Um so there's the idea of local models and global models. And so local models
and global models. And so local models are are basically models where this cap
are are basically models where this cap on computation happens within a local
on computation happens within a local window. And then global models you have
window. And then global models you have a cap on you might or might not have a
a cap on you might or might not have a cap on computation but that cap on
cap on computation but that cap on computation is not localized. So you can
computation is not localized. So you can pass information uh throughout the
pass information uh throughout the entire sequence. And the I'd say almost
entire sequence. And the I'd say almost all of the models uh that exist nowadays
all of the models uh that exist nowadays or are widely popular nowadays are some
or are widely popular nowadays are some variety of hybrid model where they have
variety of hybrid model where they have many local computations and then one
many local computations and then one global computation then many local
global computation then many local computations one global computation
computations one global computation and specifically I'm going to talk about
and specifically I'm going to talk about six uh models that we have here. So uh
six uh models that we have here. So uh the most recent Quen model uh has uh
the most recent Quen model uh has uh local computation of uh gated delta net.
local computation of uh gated delta net. I'll explain all of these uh or most of
I'll explain all of these uh or most of these in a bit. And then um sparse
these in a bit. And then um sparse retrieval uh for the global computation
retrieval uh for the global computation and the ratio is 3:1.
and the ratio is 3:1. Uh GLM 5.3 is uh also a variety of delta
Uh GLM 5.3 is uh also a variety of delta um and sparse attention uh with 3:1.
um and sparse attention uh with 3:1. Um
Um uh Kim K3 is uh a variety of Delta and
uh Kim K3 is uh a variety of Delta and um this is a dense uh dense attention
um this is a dense uh dense attention 3:1.
3:1. Uh Neimotron is Mamba uh which is uh
Uh Neimotron is Mamba uh which is uh kind of like recurrent style model
kind of like recurrent style model and uh dense attention 4:1.
and uh dense attention 4:1. um to uh window uh sliding window
um to uh window uh sliding window attention uh dense attention 5 to one
attention uh dense attention 5 to one and deepseek's a little bit different.
and deepseek's a little bit different. It kind of has uh window windowed
It kind of has uh window windowed attention but then some uh sparsity uh
attention but then some uh sparsity uh sparse stuff with interle branches. So
sparse stuff with interle branches. So um basically the the standard way of
um basically the the standard way of doing things is hybrid model uh with
doing things is hybrid model uh with some sort of local thing and uh either
some sort of local thing and uh either sparse or dense uh global attention.
sparse or dense uh global attention. So I'm I'm going to be talking about
So I'm I'm going to be talking about this. I'm not going to go into like a
this. I'm not going to go into like a ton of details for all of them, but uh
ton of details for all of them, but uh it should be enough that you could be
it should be enough that you could be able to look them up later.
So the first one is uh sliding window attention. And this is maybe the the
attention. And this is maybe the the simplest conceptually. And what you do
simplest conceptually. And what you do is you take chunks or uh you take chunks
is you take chunks or uh you take chunks of the output and basically you're able
of the output and basically you're able to attend to your current chunk and um
to attend to your current chunk and um all of the previous chunks and uh
all of the previous chunks and uh or not all of the previous chunks, a
or not all of the previous chunks, a fixed number of previous chunks. So if
fixed number of previous chunks. So if this is your current chunk, um it might
this is your current chunk, um it might be a chunk of like 512 tokens or
be a chunk of like 512 tokens or something like this. You would have an
something like this. You would have an additional 512 and 512 tokens in the
additional 512 and 512 tokens in the previous chunks and you would attend to
previous chunks and you would attend to those. Um so pretty simple, no changes
those. Um so pretty simple, no changes to attention, but you have something
to attention, but you have something like this. But the nice thing about this
like this. But the nice thing about this is on the first layer you're passing
is on the first layer you're passing information from the previous one or two
information from the previous one or two chunks, but on the next layer the uh
chunks, but on the next layer the uh previous chunks also have information
previous chunks also have information from their previous chunks. And so you
from their previous chunks. And so you kind of get this gradually expanding
kind of get this gradually expanding window. Um
window. Um so uh this uh this is pretty widely
so uh this uh this is pretty widely used.
Um but the more popular way of doing things nowadays is using some variety of
things nowadays is using some variety of linear attention.
linear attention. And so the way uh linear attention works
And so the way uh linear attention works is basically we take our uh standard
is basically we take our uh standard attention and standard attention has
attention and standard attention has this um softmax operation included in
this um softmax operation included in it. And this is the reason why it's hard
it. And this is the reason why it's hard to compute because you're taking the
to compute because you're taking the exponent and um and dividing. And
exponent and um and dividing. And because you do this there's you
because you do this there's you basically have no choice but to expand
basically have no choice but to expand all of the uh key and query computations
all of the uh key and query computations uh like key query multiplication
uh like key query multiplication computations in and be uh quadratic uh
computations in and be uh quadratic uh quadratic
quadratic complexity.
complexity. What linear attention does is you
What linear attention does is you basically start from this uh kind of
basically start from this uh kind of standard attention formulation but you
standard attention formulation but you take you remove the softmax and the
take you remove the softmax and the normalization here or I mean the
normalization here or I mean the normalization doesn't really matter but
normalization doesn't really matter but you remove the softmax and you get just
you remove the softmax and you get just the key query multiplication
the key query multiplication and [clears throat]
and [clears throat] this is definitely less expressive
this is definitely less expressive because basically what you're doing is
because basically what you're doing is you're moving
you're moving from something that
from something that takes in a bunch of uh like numbers.
Anyway, like pretend pretend that this bottom one adds up to one, but you're
bottom one adds up to one, but you're going from a thing that takes a bunch of
going from a thing that takes a bunch of real numbers and normalizes them into
real numbers and normalizes them into probability like numbers that are
probability like numbers that are between zero and one and add to one. Um,
between zero and one and add to one. Um, so this nonlinearity allows you to focus
so this nonlinearity allows you to focus on like only some of the previous uh
on like only some of the previous uh like tokens. And this is kind of the
like tokens. And this is kind of the good point of attention. That's the
good point of attention. That's the selling point of attention that allows
selling point of attention that allows you to focus on the relevant previous
you to focus on the relevant previous context. And you're basically taking
context. And you're basically taking away that ability, right? You're you're
away that ability, right? You're you're removing the relative comparisons and
removing the relative comparisons and just getting um the the dotproduct
just getting um the the dotproduct between the queries and keys. But it
between the queries and keys. But it allows you to do something really uh
allows you to do something really uh nice which is that you can use uh the
nice which is that you can use uh the associative
associative uh you can use associivity and basically
uh you can use associivity and basically rearrange
rearrange so that um you can convert the sum of
so that um you can convert the sum of all the key and value uh multiplications
all the key and value uh multiplications before into a single uh state matrix.
before into a single uh state matrix. And so this state matrix is essentially
And so this state matrix is essentially a function that map it's a linear
a function that map it's a linear function that maps from a query to a
function that maps from a query to a value. So attention is also a linear
value. So attention is also a linear function that maps from a query to a
function that maps from a query to a value. So if I go back to this here
value. So if I go back to this here you're basically calculating you're
you're basically calculating you're taking the query you're calculating the
taking the query you're calculating the attention over all the keys you're
attention over all the keys you're multiplying it by the values and you're
multiplying it by the values and you're getting a value here. Um and this state
getting a value here. Um and this state matrix is also that. But the nice part
matrix is also that. But the nice part about it is this state matrix can be
about it is this state matrix can be decomposed. So you can update it. You
decomposed. So you can update it. You can keep this state matrix around and
can keep this state matrix around and update it in constant time every time
update it in constant time every time you get a new value. So this essentially
you get a new value. So this essentially becomes like a recurrent neural network.
becomes like a recurrent neural network. So it it allows you to update the state
So it it allows you to update the state matrix um in linear time without having
matrix um in linear time without having uh without requiring the quadratic
uh without requiring the quadratic computation.
computation. So
So this basically solves your quadratic
this basically solves your quadratic problem and it solves it so much
problem and it solves it so much that um O of N squ becomes O of N.
that um O of N squ becomes O of N. There's no like there's no even W term
There's no like there's no even W term in this because uh each time you're uh
in this because uh each time you're uh you're updating based entirely on the
you're updating based entirely on the previous state. Um but there's there's
previous state. Um but there's there's caveats here. So um is this clear though
caveats here. So um is this clear though uh so far?
uh so far? Okay, cool.
Okay, cool. Um, so the big caveat is exactly the
Um, so the big caveat is exactly the caveat I mentioned before. Like this is
caveat I mentioned before. Like this is just a less expressive function. Um, and
just a less expressive function. Um, and it doesn't allow you to make like
it doesn't allow you to make like relative comparisons between the
relative comparisons between the previous tokens, that sort of thing. So
previous tokens, that sort of thing. So there's a bunch of uh workarounds around
there's a bunch of uh workarounds around this to try to make a more expressive
this to try to make a more expressive function that nonetheless is useful in
function that nonetheless is useful in um in kind of uh doing attention-like
um in kind of uh doing attention-like calculations. And so um most of these
calculations. And so um most of these are
are if you dig deep into the math in them,
if you dig deep into the math in them, they're basically trying to become
they're basically trying to become better predictors of the final value
better predictors of the final value that you would get from attention. Um
that you would get from attention. Um and you you can dig into the papers to
and you you can dig into the papers to see how that works, but I'm going to
see how that works, but I'm going to explain them mostly uh mechanistically
explain them mostly uh mechanistically here. And so um the first thing is
here. And so um the first thing is Delta. And the idea behind deltaNet is
Delta. And the idea behind deltaNet is um you can predict what
um you can predict what um
um you can essentially predict what value
you can essentially predict what value you would want to be getting from the uh
you would want to be getting from the uh from the calculation of uh KT
from the calculation of uh KT um and S. And so you know KT here is uh
um and S. And so you know KT here is uh the key at time step t and you are
the key at time step t and you are comparing it with the matrix at time
comparing it with the matrix at time step t uh t minus one and uh you're
step t uh t minus one and uh you're calculating this v hat t and
calculating this v hat t and on the other hand you um so basically
on the other hand you um so basically this this is the prediction that you
this this is the prediction that you would get of kt But on the other hand,
would get of kt But on the other hand, you know what the uh output VT should be
you know what the uh output VT should be uh based on um what the query times uh
uh based on um what the query times uh or based on uh what the
or based on uh what the Hang on one second. [laughter]
Hang on one second. [laughter] I don't want to I don't want to get this
I don't want to I don't want to get this wrong. So
you calculate KT with respect to the matrix. And you can view this matrix as
matrix. And you can view this matrix as a way of uh calculating the uh the way
a way of uh calculating the uh the way of calculating the mapping from a query
of calculating the mapping from a query to a value. And you can also get the the
to a value. And you can also get the the actual value and subtract out uh what
actual value and subtract out uh what the value you get when multiplying it
the value you get when multiplying it from the previous uh together with the
from the previous uh together with the previous matrix is. And this is
previous matrix is. And this is essentially the error uh that you get
essentially the error uh that you get here. And then you want to reduce the
here. And then you want to reduce the error. And so in order to reduce this
error. And so in order to reduce this error, what you do is you um essentially
error, what you do is you um essentially add in this uh this term which is KT uh
add in this uh this term which is KT uh times the error term. And after you do
times the error term. And after you do this, if you multiply in KT to the new
this, if you multiply in KT to the new matrix, you will no longer have any
matrix, you will no longer have any error. But you don't want to make an
error. But you don't want to make an update that is too big. So you add this
update that is too big. So you add this beta term. This is essentially a
beta term. This is essentially a learning, it's similar to a learning
learning, it's similar to a learning rate. And this learning rate will make
rate. And this learning rate will make the updates uh smaller. And so uh if you
the updates uh smaller. And so uh if you if you do this, this allows you to
if you do this, this allows you to basically nudge the matrix in the
basically nudge the matrix in the direction of uh the in the direction
direction of uh the in the direction that will cause a query that looks like
that will cause a query that looks like the current key to output the value that
the current key to output the value that you want essentially. So it's it's
you want essentially. So it's it's reducing the error uh reducing the error
reducing the error uh reducing the error in the prediction of the value that you
in the prediction of the value that you want.
So um as I said this is going to be a little bit high level. Um the the papers
little bit high level. Um the the papers are are pretty good uh descriptions of
are are pretty good uh descriptions of this.
this. Um so after this um this basically what
Um so after this um this basically what this is doing is this is pushing you in
this is doing is this is pushing you in the direction of the uh of making the
the direction of the uh of making the the matrix a better predictor of the uh
the matrix a better predictor of the uh the value. But one problem with this is
the value. But one problem with this is you can build up lots and lots of
you can build up lots and lots of context uh from the previous uh spots
context uh from the previous uh spots and linear attention doesn't have any
and linear attention doesn't have any mechanism to prevent very far away cont
mechanism to prevent very far away cont uh context from having a bad
uh context from having a bad influence on your next predictions. And
influence on your next predictions. And so if you have like a very weird key far
so if you have like a very weird key far back in the future, it might have a very
back in the future, it might have a very big influence on you in the f uh in the
big influence on you in the f uh in the future. And so the way they fix this is
future. And so the way they fix this is basically they have a decay term to make
basically they have a decay term to make uh to make the
uh to make the matrix decay
matrix decay a little bit at every time step. And by
a little bit at every time step. And by decaying the matrix a little bit at
decaying the matrix a little bit at every time step, they're basically
every time step, they're basically discounting the the far in the past
discounting the the far in the past context. And so you multiply um the
context. And so you multiply um the matrix by alpha t and then you add this
matrix by alpha t and then you add this uh st tilda into uh into your
uh st tilda into uh into your calculation here and update the matrix.
calculation here and update the matrix. And so the stronger you make this decay
And so the stronger you make this decay basically the the more quickly uh it
basically the the more quickly uh it will forget the previous context. And so
will forget the previous context. And so you can make this more local or or less
you can make this more local or or less local.
And so this is uh gated delta is used in the Quen models. So it's one of the more
the Quen models. So it's one of the more uh the more popular methods now. Um but
uh the more popular methods now. Um but both uh GLM and uh KI which are kind of
both uh GLM and uh KI which are kind of two of the state-of-the-art models use a
two of the state-of-the-art models use a slightly more expressive version of this
slightly more expressive version of this uh where they basically have a per
uh where they basically have a per element uh decay term. So each element
element uh decay term. So each element can decay at a different speed. And uh
can decay at a different speed. And uh because each element decays at a
because each element decays at a different speed, you can have some uh
different speed, you can have some uh portions of the context that uh you know
portions of the context that uh you know carry over very long time periods, some
carry over very long time periods, some portions of the context that carry over
portions of the context that carry over very short time periods.
Cool. So hopefully this was more or less uh more or less legible. Um
uh more or less legible. Um any any questions here?
any any questions here? Long long story short, it's basically a
Long long story short, it's basically a way to turn uh into
way to turn uh into um it's a way to turn
um it's a way to turn the idea of attention to something that
the idea of attention to something that you can calculate um in context. Mamba
you can calculate um in context. Mamba is uh something that's very similar um
is uh something that's very similar um but it's a little bit more
but it's a little bit more mathematically involved um uh and I I
mathematically involved um uh and I I decided to skip over it. uh I covered it
decided to skip over it. uh I covered it more in the uh language model uh
more in the uh language model uh description course but similar idea but
description course but similar idea but just a bit more complex uh in the math.
just a bit more complex uh in the math. So the next thing I'd like to talk about
So the next thing I'd like to talk about is sparse attention. And so sparse
is sparse attention. And so sparse attention is uh basically looking up a
attention is uh basically looking up a not attending to everything in the
not attending to everything in the previous context but only attending to
previous context but only attending to some things in the previous context. And
some things in the previous context. And essentially you limit the number of
essentially you limit the number of things that you look up in the previous
things that you look up in the previous context. There's a few ways you can do
context. There's a few ways you can do it. Um originally in there was a sparse
it. Um originally in there was a sparse attention paper by OpenAI uh quite a
attention paper by OpenAI uh quite a while ago like 5 years ago or something
while ago like 5 years ago or something like this. Um and basically uh what they
like this. Um and basically uh what they did was they had sparse attention every
did was they had sparse attention every you know uh 512 tokens or something like
you know uh 512 tokens or something like this. And what this does is it means
this. And what this does is it means that you still have a fixed it's still
that you still have a fixed it's still quadratic in the sequence length but
quadratic in the sequence length but it's 512 times less than if you attended
it's 512 times less than if you attended to every token and that's like good
to every token and that's like good enough uh that you can manage to
enough uh that you can manage to calculate it over the context that
calculate it over the context that you're interested in.
you're interested in. Another option is to do um content
Another option is to do um content dependent sparse attention. And
dependent sparse attention. And basically what this does is you have a
basically what this does is you have a very cheap way of calculating attention.
very cheap way of calculating attention. Like for example, you can down project
Like for example, you can down project the attention vectors to be very very
the attention vectors to be very very small and then you do attention over
small and then you do attention over these very very small uh attention
these very very small uh attention vectors. You pick the top k ones and
vectors. You pick the top k ones and then you do full attention over the top
then you do full attention over the top k. So uh that's uh another way that you
k. So uh that's uh another way that you can do this
can do this and this is what's used in deepseek.
and this is what's used in deepseek. Yeah.
Yeah. >> How do we define the metric for which we
>> How do we define the metric for which we do the top similarity compared in this
do the top similarity compared in this in the shrine space we just do like
in the shrine space we just do like coine distance.
coine distance. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah. >> Yeah. I I think it's typically not
>> Yeah. I I think it's typically not cosine but it's just product but yeah
cosine but it's just product but yeah >> I I I think although maybe maybe they're
>> I I I think although maybe maybe they're normalizing beforehand. They actually
normalizing beforehand. They actually don't know that detail.
don't know that detail. Any other questions?
Any other questions? So basically um these
So basically um these th this is a very very cheap way to
th this is a very very cheap way to achieve global attention because you can
achieve global attention because you can just uh write a kernel that will do this
just uh write a kernel that will do this for you. Um this over here will uh
for you. Um this over here will uh require you to have two passes, but you
require you to have two passes, but you know it's potentially uh more accurate.
know it's potentially uh more accurate. So um I I've seen both of these used
So um I I've seen both of these used pretty widely.
So a final um a final thing is KV compression. How many people saw this in
compression. How many people saw this in a language modeling course?
a language modeling course? Maybe some people. Okay. Um so I will uh
Maybe some people. Okay. Um so I will uh I'll explain this. So basically um this
I'll explain this. So basically um this is standard multi head attention. And so
is standard multi head attention. And so in standard multi-head attention, you
in standard multi-head attention, you have a bunch of heads and each one has
have a bunch of heads and each one has values and keys and all of these are a
values and keys and all of these are a certain dimension. So they're like
certain dimension. So they're like dimension, let's say they're dimension D
dimension, let's say they're dimension D and you have uh you have like a certain
and you have uh you have like a certain number of heads. Let's say that's H. Um
number of heads. Let's say that's H. Um so
the two main ways that people solve uh or help uh this problem of having very
or help uh this problem of having very uh large and expensive KV caches is uh
uh large and expensive KV caches is uh grouped query attention. And grouped
grouped query attention. And grouped query attention basically uh just uses a
query attention basically uh just uses a smaller number than h um you usually h
smaller number than h um you usually h divided by some uh power of two uh
divided by some uh power of two uh number of uh keys and values. And
number of uh keys and values. And because it's the KV cache, it's not the
because it's the KV cache, it's not the KVQ cache. Um
KVQ cache. Um if you reduce the number of uh keys and
if you reduce the number of uh keys and values that are used, you reduce the
values that are used, you reduce the amount of memory that you need to hold
amount of memory that you need to hold the KV cache. This is really important
the KV cache. This is really important because if it gets very large then um it
because if it gets very large then um it limits the number you can fit on one GPU
limits the number you can fit on one GPU and so this can usually be reduced by
and so this can usually be reduced by like four or by eight or something like
like four or by eight or something like that. Um multiquery attention is just
that. Um multiquery attention is just like grouped query attention with a
like grouped query attention with a single one. So you can kind of almost
single one. So you can kind of almost skip over that. You already know what it
skip over that. You already know what it means. Um multi head latent attention
means. Um multi head latent attention the the um
the the um is essentially down projecting uh the
is essentially down projecting uh the size of the keys and values. So it's not
size of the keys and values. So it's not reducing the number of heads, it's
reducing the number of heads, it's making each head smaller. And so this is
making each head smaller. And so this is similar to what I talked about with the
similar to what I talked about with the top K attention. Um and of course you
top K attention. Um and of course you can combine both of these together as
can combine both of these together as well. You could have group query
well. You could have group query attention with um you know smaller uh
attention with um you know smaller uh keys of values.
Okay, cool. Um so the these are the method the
Um so the these are the method the architectural methods that people use to
architectural methods that people use to handle very long contexts and with these
handle very long contexts and with these um you can handle up to a million uh
um you can handle up to a million uh tokens. So like this is uh you know this
tokens. So like this is uh you know this makes the efficiency possible.
makes the efficiency possible. The next thing is uh training long
The next thing is uh training long context models. And this is actually uh
context models. And this is actually uh pretty hard. And the reason why is
pretty hard. And the reason why is because um if we want something to
because um if we want something to handle 128k tokens or even more, there's
handle 128k tokens or even more, there's actually not that much data on the
actually not that much data on the internet that is 128k coherent tokens.
internet that is 128k coherent tokens. Um it's actually a lot of a lot of data.
Um it's actually a lot of a lot of data. it's more than most Wikipedia articles,
it's more than most Wikipedia articles, you know, um you're starting to get in
you know, um you're starting to get in the in the order of like having a book
the in the order of like having a book uh that you need to have and there's not
uh that you need to have and there's not that many books on the internet. So,
that many books on the internet. So, typically what you do is you start out
typically what you do is you start out with like short pre-training. Um you do
with like short pre-training. Um you do more continued training with longer
more continued training with longer documents and then you do long
documents and then you do long adaptation.
adaptation. Um I wrote packed sequences here. Um,
Um I wrote packed sequences here. Um, but packed sequences are are useful can
but packed sequences are are useful can be useful for efficiency, but they're
be useful for efficiency, but they're not super useful for learning long
not super useful for learning long contexts because um every time you like
contexts because um every time you like let's say you pack 10 documents into a
let's say you pack 10 documents into a sequence, you're not learning to attend
sequence, you're not learning to attend across the documents and in fact you
across the documents and in fact you probably should not be. So um you really
probably should not be. So um you really need coherent uh long sets of data to do
need coherent uh long sets of data to do adaptation to very long contexts.
Um so I'm going to talk about a few things that we do here. Um the first
things that we do here. Um the first thing I'm going to talk about is uh
thing I'm going to talk about is uh handling positional encodings. Um so
handling positional encodings. Um so absolute positional encodings uh I I
absolute positional encodings uh I I hope everybody has seen in their
hope everybody has seen in their language modeling class. Um but
language modeling class. Um but basically uh each individual
basically uh each individual entry in the uh
entry in the uh each individual word embedding uh gets a
each individual word embedding uh gets a position vector and that position vector
position vector and that position vector is typically calculated by uh some sort
is typically calculated by uh some sort of function like using signs and
of function like using signs and cosiness and other stuff like this. So
cosiness and other stuff like this. So hopefully you know most people have seen
hopefully you know most people have seen this. So I'll I'll kind of skip over
this. So I'll I'll kind of skip over that. Also maybe most people have seen
that. Also maybe most people have seen rope. Are people generally familiar with
rope. Are people generally familiar with rope? Okay, I see a fair number of
rope? Okay, I see a fair number of people. I see actually less people uh
people. I see actually less people uh than I would have expected, but um uh
than I would have expected, but um uh maybe people are just uh not interested
maybe people are just uh not interested in raising your hand. Um [laughter] but
in raising your hand. Um [laughter] but uh but basically um rope rope is pretty
uh but basically um rope rope is pretty elegant mathematically in my opinion. Uh
elegant mathematically in my opinion. Uh basically the problem they were trying
basically the problem they were trying to solve is they wanted to have a
to solve is they wanted to have a positional embedding. um where the
positional embedding. um where the positional uh or positional encoding
positional uh or positional encoding where the positional encoding is
where the positional encoding is entirely
entirely determined by the relative distance uh
determined by the relative distance uh between two tokens.
between two tokens. And the
And the reason why they wanted to do this is
reason why they wanted to do this is they didn't they didn't want the
they didn't they didn't want the absolute position to have an effect on
absolute position to have an effect on uh they didn't want the absolute
uh they didn't want the absolute position to have an effect on whether
position to have an effect on whether two tokens would attend to each other.
two tokens would attend to each other. And so
And so this is this has been quite effective
this is this has been quite effective and a lot of uh a lot of models use
and a lot of uh a lot of models use rope. Um the the math I'm not going to
rope. Um the the math I'm not going to go through here because it's kind of not
go through here because it's kind of not the main point, but they do some
the main point, but they do some interesting stuff with rotations and
interesting stuff with rotations and imaginary numbers and stuff like this.
imaginary numbers and stuff like this. Um but there's also this like super
Um but there's also this like super counterintuitive
counterintuitive uh nope.
uh nope. which is uh don't don't use positional
which is uh don't don't use positional encodings at all. Um and if you took
encodings at all. Um and if you took your uh class on transformers
your uh class on transformers uh you might have heard this scary stuff
uh you might have heard this scary stuff which is like you need positional
which is like you need positional encodings for transformers because
encodings for transformers because otherwise something in position one in
otherwise something in position one in position five will have exactly the same
position five will have exactly the same representation. So if you have like this
representation. So if you have like this this is a cat but this is not a cat it
this is a cat but this is not a cat it will attend to both of the cats the same
will attend to both of the cats the same amount or something like this. Um
theoretically when the transformers were originally created um this might have
originally created um this might have been true but now actually it's it's not
been true but now actually it's it's not true anymore based on the transformers
true anymore based on the transformers we use now. Um anybody have an idea
we use now. Um anybody have an idea why this is the case? I've kind of given
why this is the case? I've kind of given a hint in the slide but
a hint in the slide but you might also need to know a little bit
you might also need to know a little bit of the history of transformers uh which
of the history of transformers uh which is uh before we were using encoder
is uh before we were using encoder decoder models uh where the encoders
decoder models uh where the encoders encoded all of the input and then the
encoded all of the input and then the decoders uh generated the output any
decoders uh generated the output any idea
idea >> because we're doing causal masking
>> because we're doing causal masking exactly so um to elaborate on that a
exactly so um to elaborate on that a little bit if I go back to our
little bit if I go back to our transformer equation
Um, we have the keys um, and the queries. And if we look at the queries,
queries. And if we look at the queries, even if you have cat at position two and
even if you have cat at position two and cat at position five, the cat at
cat at position five, the cat at position two is only attending to the
position two is only attending to the previous token where the cat at position
previous token where the cat at position five is attending to the previous four
five is attending to the previous four tokens. Um, and so both of them are like
tokens. Um, and so both of them are like actually different. um starting at least
actually different. um starting at least in the first layer of attention. And so
in the first layer of attention. And so you can tell like even if they are
you can tell like even if they are exactly the same word, the embeddings
exactly the same word, the embeddings starting in the first layer of attention
starting in the first layer of attention will will not be different. And there's
will will not be different. And there's kind of uh this counterintuitive paper
kind of uh this counterintuitive paper that demonstrates that you don't need uh
that demonstrates that you don't need uh positional encodings at all. And this is
positional encodings at all. And this is especially true um this is in auto
especially true um this is in auto reggressive uh transformers. In non-auto
reggressive uh transformers. In non-auto reggressive transformers where you're
reggressive transformers where you're attending all the tokens are attending
attending all the tokens are attending to each other. You still do need
to each other. You still do need positional encodings. Um
positional encodings. Um this is especially true when we start
this is especially true when we start talking about like gated delta because
talking about like gated delta because gated delta has like the decay term and
gated delta has like the decay term and uh other things like this which causes
uh other things like this which causes each uh token to be different. So once
each uh token to be different. So once we start having those sort of local
we start having those sort of local biases, we actually don't need
biases, we actually don't need positional uh encodings anymore.
positional uh encodings anymore. Um
Um and
and if you uh if you look um
if you uh if you look um we uh the first two here have rope uh or
we uh the first two here have rope uh or at least partial rope. The second two
at least partial rope. The second two have nope uh no positional attend
have nope uh no positional attend encodings. Um the the fourth one uh
encodings. Um the the fourth one uh relies entirely on implicit order and
relies entirely on implicit order and mamba and some of them in uh and inkling
mamba and some of them in uh and inkling has relative positional encodings. So
has relative positional encodings. So you can see that it's kind of like half
you can see that it's kind of like half split between having relative positional
split between having relative positional encodings and not at all. But like let's
encodings and not at all. But like let's say we did have positional encodings. Uh
say we did have positional encodings. Uh one thing you need to worry about for
one thing you need to worry about for long context is uh position
long context is uh position interpolation or position extension. And
interpolation or position extension. And what this means is if you have a
what this means is if you have a pre-training range, um, you need to
pre-training range, um, you need to essentially extend your model so that
essentially extend your model so that it's able to handle longer sequences.
it's able to handle longer sequences. And so the the promise of rope was that
And so the the promise of rope was that rope relied only on the relative
rope relied only on the relative position uh between the different tokens
position uh between the different tokens in the output. But
in the output. But that that's fine as long as the relative
that that's fine as long as the relative position is only um well okay there
position is only um well okay there there's two reasons why this is not
there's two reasons why this is not fine. So number one if you're training
fine. So number one if you're training on
on sequences of length L and then you
sequences of length L and then you extend to sequences uh of length SL then
extend to sequences uh of length SL then it's never seen two tokens attend to
it's never seen two tokens attend to each other over a distance of more than
each other over a distance of more than L. So the tokens that are more than L
L. So the tokens that are more than L away from each other are going to have
away from each other are going to have problems attending to each other and
problems attending to each other and you're not going to be able to uh manage
you're not going to be able to uh manage that very well. Um the other problem is
that very well. Um the other problem is that actually relative positional
that actually relative positional encodings are only one part of the story
encodings are only one part of the story and like actually the auto reggressive
and like actually the auto reggressive mask has an effect in all these other
mask has an effect in all these other things. So you can't just take rope and
things. So you can't just take rope and expect it to work uh really well on
expect it to work uh really well on longer sequences.
longer sequences. And so the typical way you fix this is
And so the typical way you fix this is there's a parameter in rope that
there's a parameter in rope that basically
basically uh
uh let me see if I have it in my slide.
let me see if I have it in my slide. So I I don't I don't really have it in
So I I don't I don't really have it in my slide, but there's basically a um a
my slide, but there's basically a um a parameter in rope theta that uh tells
parameter in rope theta that uh tells you how much you rotate at each time
you how much you rotate at each time step. and you divide this theta by the
step. and you divide this theta by the uh multiplier by which you extended the
uh multiplier by which you extended the sequence. And so basically you're
sequence. And so basically you're stretching the rope position so that the
stretching the rope position so that the rope uh position at position zero would
rope uh position at position zero would um or the rope position at position like
um or the rope position at position like five would be 5s uh would be equivalent
five would be 5s uh would be equivalent to the position 5s in your uh extended
to the position 5s in your uh extended context.
context. And there's also um a more sophisticated
And there's also um a more sophisticated way of doing this called yarn uh which
way of doing this called yarn uh which basically is uh similar
basically is uh similar in spirit uh to like the delta uh the ki
in spirit uh to like the delta uh the ki delta attention
delta attention um which
um which basically said that we want some of them
basically said that we want some of them to be very long distance and some of
to be very long distance and some of them to not be very long distance. In
them to not be very long distance. In yarn essentially you have some of them
yarn essentially you have some of them be uh extended more and some of them be
be uh extended more and some of them be extended less and so you don't um you
extended less and so you don't um you don't necessarily interpolate all of
don't necessarily interpolate all of them at the same frequency.
So um yeah in the interest of time I'm not going to go into like a lot of
not going to go into like a lot of detail about this but basically these
detail about this but basically these are um uh these are the various methods
are um uh these are the various methods that you can use here.
So, um, I'd like to talk a little bit now, um,
I'd like to talk a little bit now, um, taking a step back from the detailed
taking a step back from the detailed modeling stuff and going into the data
modeling stuff and going into the data that you can use to train this. So, um,
that you can use to train this. So, um, as I mentioned before, packed examples,
as I mentioned before, packed examples, you can just pack a whole bunch of stuff
you can just pack a whole bunch of stuff in there, um, a whole bunch of documents
in there, um, a whole bunch of documents in into your context length. And this
in into your context length. And this will work at training models to be able
will work at training models to be able to process things near the end of your
to process things near the end of your context window. But what it won't work
context window. But what it won't work for is the kind of global coherence. And
for is the kind of global coherence. And um so there's a number of different ways
um so there's a number of different ways that people do this. One way is just to
that people do this. One way is just to find um very long documents uh like
find um very long documents uh like books or something like this. There
books or something like this. There aren't a lot of these uh but there are
aren't a lot of these uh but there are books. There are code bases and code
books. There are code bases and code bases tend to be coherent. So you can
bases tend to be coherent. So you can just download a big codebase and that
just download a big codebase and that will definitely have more tokens. Um
will definitely have more tokens. Um multi-document corpora of some kind. So,
multi-document corpora of some kind. So, you know, like uh you can get a whole
you know, like uh you can get a whole bunch of documents that are on the same
bunch of documents that are on the same topic and then at least you'll have
topic and then at least you'll have topical coherence between them. Um I've
topical coherence between them. Um I've also seen people train on patents
also seen people train on patents because patents have like there's lots
because patents have like there's lots of public data for them and you can kind
of public data for them and you can kind of link link them together.
of link link them together. A big source nowadays is agent
A big source nowadays is agent trajectories because you know agents can
trajectories because you know agents can make very very long trajectories if you
make very very long trajectories if you just interact with them for a little
just interact with them for a little while. So that's another one. And then
while. So that's another one. And then you can also create synthetic tasks and
you can also create synthetic tasks and a lot of the evaluations are synthetic
a lot of the evaluations are synthetic tasks. So you can do that as well.
Um and I I have some examples of how the models do this. Um a lot of the model
models do this. Um a lot of the model training companies don't like to share
training companies don't like to share these details with you because this is
these details with you because this is like if they release their um well so
like if they release their um well so number one the closed models like
number one the closed models like anthropic open AAI you know those places
anthropic open AAI you know those places uh uh Gemini they will not release even
uh uh Gemini they will not release even their architectural details the open
their architectural details the open model companies have to release their
model companies have to release their architectural details otherwise you
architectural details otherwise you can't run their model so what do they
can't run their model so what do they keep secret they keep their data mixes
keep secret they keep their data mixes and their their training strategy secret
and their their training strategy secret so um this there's a lot less detailed
so um this there's a lot less detailed stuff that we can say. Um, but there's
stuff that we can say. Um, but there's uh all of them explain all of the ones
uh all of them explain all of the ones in here explain a little bit about their
in here explain a little bit about their data mixtures and they are things like
data mixtures and they are things like uh cleaned up sampled documents and
uh cleaned up sampled documents and video um documents, repository files,
video um documents, repository files, issue, PRs, uh long document QA,
issue, PRs, uh long document QA, scientific papers and technical reports.
scientific papers and technical reports. And then uh they also create a bunch of
And then uh they also create a bunch of synthetic tasks. And typically they have
synthetic tasks. And typically they have a scaling strategy of like 8 64 256 1
a scaling strategy of like 8 64 256 1 million uh that that sort of stuff as
million uh that that sort of stuff as well.
Oh yes. Um [clears throat] one other
one other logistical detail that you might need to
logistical detail that you might need to deal with um or might not need to deal
deal with um or might not need to deal with depending on the size of the model
with depending on the size of the model you're training. like for example for
you're training. like for example for your project if you want to start
your project if you want to start dealing with um uh larger models is
dealing with um uh larger models is context parallelism and basically what
context parallelism and basically what this means is there's a bunch of uh ways
this means is there's a bunch of uh ways to do parallelism when training models I
to do parallelism when training models I wrote context parallelism up here what
wrote context parallelism up here what are two other ways uh that you can
are two other ways uh that you can parallelize models during model training
parallelize models during model training or serving
or serving >> yes
>> data parallelism >> yeah you you said a more specific
>> yeah you you said a more specific example of the second one but data
example of the second one but data parallelism and I would say model
parallelism and I would say model parallelism in general and model
parallelism in general and model parallelism can have lots of varieties.
parallelism can have lots of varieties. It can have uh expert parallelism where
It can have uh expert parallelism where you have different experts on different
you have different experts on different machines uh tensor more generally tensor
machines uh tensor more generally tensor parallelism where you split um uh the uh
parallelism where you split um uh the uh the parameters and you can also have
the parameters and you can also have pipeline parallelism where you have
pipeline parallelism where you have different layers on different uh
different layers on different uh different devices. But context
different devices. But context parallelism starts becoming import more
parallelism starts becoming import more important for agents because when you
important for agents because when you train agents you want to train them on
train agents you want to train them on very long contexts. And so uh the way
very long contexts. And so uh the way this works is you will compute like one
this works is you will compute like one part of the context uh the keys and
part of the context uh the keys and values. So you send it to the next
values. So you send it to the next device calculate the keys and values for
device calculate the keys and values for the next for that part send it to the
the next for that part send it to the next device uh and etc etc. So um this
next device uh and etc etc. So um this is uh very useful. It's really important
is uh very useful. It's really important if you start getting above like 32k
if you start getting above like 32k 32k context or so. Um, but it's also a
32k context or so. Um, but it's also a pain because
pain because you have the
um you have all the modeling people saying
you have all the modeling people saying I want my I want my KI delta attention
I want my I want my KI delta attention and then you have all the info people
and then you have all the info people saying but wait I need to implement a
saying but wait I need to implement a context parallel kernel for KI delta
context parallel kernel for KI delta attention and make sure it actually
attention and make sure it actually works and you can back prop through it
works and you can back prop through it and all of these other things. So um I I
and all of these other things. So um I I personally had an experience where I was
personally had an experience where I was trying to train uh Quen uh for uh like a
trying to train uh Quen uh for uh like a smaller quen model like 135 uh 35b and
smaller quen model like 135 uh 35b and uh I I wanted to go do use context
uh I I wanted to go do use context parallelism on it and it's like there's
parallelism on it and it's like there's no kernel for gated delta net anywhere
no kernel for gated delta net anywhere on the internet and so um you need to uh
on the internet and so um you need to uh you need to either go in and implement
you need to either go in and implement that kernel or decide to do something
that kernel or decide to do something else. So um th those two can conflict
else. So um th those two can conflict some of the times. So be be aware I
some of the times. So be be aware I guess
um the the good news is for like standard attention and sliding window
standard attention and sliding window attention and stuff like that all of
attention and stuff like that all of those will have uh kernels more easily
those will have uh kernels more easily implemented. The hard parts are where
implemented. The hard parts are where you're like not doing a standard
you're like not doing a standard attention operation.
Okay. So the next part I'd like to talk about is prompt and KV caching. This is
about is prompt and KV caching. This is uh very important even if you're not the
uh very important even if you're not the person who's implementing the language
person who's implementing the language model, but also if you're just a person
model, but also if you're just a person who's um
who's um like running agents uh yourself, but I'm
like running agents uh yourself, but I'm going to talk about uh the the technical
going to talk about uh the the technical details of how it's implemented. So, you
details of how it's implemented. So, you know, at least you you have a good uh
know, at least you you have a good uh idea about how that works. So um
idea about how that works. So um basically
basically when we I I simplified this a little bit
when we I I simplified this a little bit but when we're generating an agent call
but when we're generating an agent call we have an input uh we have an output uh
we have an input uh we have an output uh so this could be like the the messages
so this could be like the the messages and tool calls and then we have the tool
and tool calls and then we have the tool result and so so
as we calculate the input we do prefill and as we calculate the output uh we do
and as we calculate the output uh we do uh basically decoding Right? And so
uh basically decoding Right? And so during prefill and decoding, we have to
during prefill and decoding, we have to calculate the KV cache. This is all done
calculate the KV cache. This is all done in a batch. Uh this is done every time
in a batch. Uh this is done every time we generate a token. But after we have
we generate a token. But after we have that, we have the uh key and value uh
that, we have the uh key and value uh for each of the positions up until the
for each of the positions up until the end of the output. And so what we can do
end of the output. And so what we can do is we can throw that in a cache and then
is we can throw that in a cache and then we don't need to calculate it anymore.
we don't need to calculate it anymore. The tool result is new uh because you
The tool result is new uh because you know we don't calculate over the tool
know we don't calculate over the tool result. So this becomes a new input and
result. So this becomes a new input and we generate an output and we get another
we generate an output and we get another tool result. And so in step two we need
tool result. And so in step two we need to calculate the KV cache over the new
to calculate the KV cache over the new input and we uh during prefill and the
input and we uh during prefill and the output but we can reuse the cache
output but we can reuse the cache and then we do that over and over and
and then we do that over and over and over again. And so as you imagine um as
over again. And so as you imagine um as you can imagine I just showed steps 1 2
you can imagine I just showed steps 1 2 3 but by the time we get to step 50 if
3 but by the time we get to step 50 if we haven't done anything tricky with our
we haven't done anything tricky with our output this is going to be 50 times
output this is going to be 50 times larger than the new input in the in the
larger than the new input in the in the output right so that's pretty
output right so that's pretty significant savings if we can cache this
significant savings if we can cache this properly
and here are some examples from actual papers uh that you know examine this and
papers uh that you know examine this and basically What we can see is this is
basically What we can see is this is like the the token length on uh
like the the token length on uh different GPUs and this is the amount of
different GPUs and this is the amount of uh of compute that you need with caching
uh of compute that you need with caching and no caching. And so the upper one of
and no caching. And so the upper one of the same color is uh or the lower one
the same color is uh or the lower one with the same color is caching and the
with the same color is caching and the the upper one is no caching. So uh
the upper one is no caching. So uh basically as the sequence gets longer
basically as the sequence gets longer the non-cashed one becomes quadratic and
the non-cashed one becomes quadratic and the cache one is is mostly linear.
This also shows up in how much you pay to run an agent. And so I I pulled all
to run an agent. And so I I pulled all of these numbers from uh the official
of these numbers from uh the official pricing. And basically you can see here
pricing. And basically you can see here that if you go through all of these uh
that if you go through all of these uh all of these numbers including the
all of these numbers including the commercial ones typically cashed tokens
commercial ones typically cashed tokens are onetenth of the price of uncashed
are onetenth of the price of uncashed tokens. And so what this means is you
tokens. And so what this means is you need to be very aware of uh whether your
need to be very aware of uh whether your tokens are being cached or not. Uh
tokens are being cached or not. Uh because if they're not being cached uh
because if they're not being cached uh you're going to be paying a lot of money
you're going to be paying a lot of money to be running your agents. Um,
to be running your agents. Um, so does anyone have an idea of what a
so does anyone have an idea of what a good uh cash hit rate is
good uh cash hit rate is if you're running an agent? Yeah.
if you're running an agent? Yeah. >> 80 to 90%.
>> 80 to 90%. >> 80 to 90%.
>> 80 to 90%. >> Yeah.
>> Um, yeah. So I I heard 80 to 90% I heard like more than 95%. I my my impression
like more than 95%. I my my impression is 90 to 95 is everything is fine. Like
is 90 to 95 is everything is fine. Like I'm I'm good with 90 to 95. If it's less
I'm I'm good with 90 to 95. If it's less than that, you might be fine, but you
than that, you might be fine, but you might be might be losing out somewhere.
might be might be losing out somewhere. Um so, uh yeah, so basically you can you
Um so, uh yeah, so basically you can you can cache most of your tokens. Um one
can cache most of your tokens. Um one other interesting thing is the output
other interesting thing is the output also tends to be five times more than
also tends to be five times more than the input. So um this is uh there's a
the input. So um this is uh there's a 50x difference between output and cached
50x difference between output and cached input which just reflects the amount of
input which just reflects the amount of uh uh the amount of cost uh savings that
uh uh the amount of cost uh savings that you can get from serving it.
you can get from serving it. So why why is caching um so much cheaper
So why why is caching um so much cheaper is maybe kind of obvious. You just need
is maybe kind of obvious. You just need to look up um you need to look up the
to look up um you need to look up the outputs. uh you just need to look these
outputs. uh you just need to look these up instead of like actually uh
up instead of like actually uh performing the calculation over them. Uh
performing the calculation over them. Uh especially the feed forward network
especially the feed forward network calculation is pretty expensive in
calculation is pretty expensive in transformers and so being able to skip
transformers and so being able to skip that is is uh particularly a win. Um but
that is is uh particularly a win. Um but how do we actually manage that? So
how do we actually manage that? So um the first thing is uh how do you hold
um the first thing is uh how do you hold it in memory? And there's two like most
it in memory? And there's two like most popular open-source
popular open-source uh two most popular open-source
uh two most popular open-source LLM serving libraries VLM and SGLANG and
LLM serving libraries VLM and SGLANG and both of them are based on an innovation
both of them are based on an innovation around the how you manage KV caching. Um
around the how you manage KV caching. Um so VLM's main technical in innovation
so VLM's main technical in innovation and like of course they have a lot more
and like of course they have a lot more stuff in there now. They're like general
stuff in there now. They're like general purpose serving libraries, but like the
purpose serving libraries, but like the main technical innovation that led to
main technical innovation that led to VLM was something called page detention.
VLM was something called page detention. And basically the way it works is you
And basically the way it works is you have physical GPU memory blocks and you
have physical GPU memory blocks and you rear you arrange them like kind of
rear you arrange them like kind of memory blocks or or disk blocks on uh
memory blocks or or disk blocks on uh like more typical uh like CPUbased
like more typical uh like CPUbased machines. And so you might have uh block
machines. And so you might have uh block zero uh block one block two that you
zero uh block one block two that you actually need to calculate and they put
actually need to calculate and they put that you know in like block one and then
that you know in like block one and then block seven and then block three or
block seven and then block three or sorry uh block seven block one block
sorry uh block seven block one block three and then you have an index to each
three and then you have an index to each one of these uh as you're generating.
one of these uh as you're generating. And the reason why they wanted to do
And the reason why they wanted to do this is they want to be able to generate
this is they want to be able to generate in parallel many sequences in parallel
in parallel many sequences in parallel and when you finish generating um you
and when you finish generating um you can like evict that from your memory and
can like evict that from your memory and so you can uh evict whole blocks at once
so you can uh evict whole blocks at once and this makes the calculation more more
and this makes the calculation more more efficient. So um this is uh one
efficient. So um this is uh one technical trick that they used to make
technical trick that they used to make this uh you know make parallel serving
this uh you know make parallel serving work.
work. Um
Um the technical innovation that kind of
the technical innovation that kind of led to SG lang in particular uh was
led to SG lang in particular uh was something called RAIX attention and this
something called RAIX attention and this is specifically focused around uh like
is specifically focused around uh like re reusing already cached uh out uh
re reusing already cached uh out uh inputs. And so what they do is they form
inputs. And so what they do is they form a a tree basically uh it's a radics tree
a a tree basically uh it's a radics tree and they use this to look up prefixes
and they use this to look up prefixes that have been used already. And so this
that have been used already. And so this uh when it first came out this was
uh when it first came out this was specifically focused around uh chat bots
specifically focused around uh chat bots like chatgpt
like chatgpt uh because you know you can have
uh because you know you can have somebody start a conversation and then
somebody start a conversation and then continue the conversation and so you'll
continue the conversation and so you'll be caching some portion of the already
be caching some portion of the already done conversation. But for uh now it's
done conversation. But for uh now it's like much much more important for agents
like much much more important for agents because agent conversations are much
because agent conversations are much longer and much more frequent. So we
longer and much more frequent. So we need this uh looking up more frequently.
Um so another uh another thing that you need to think about um which is handled
need to think about um which is handled in uh newer versions of sglang for
in uh newer versions of sglang for instance is let's say you're doing
instance is let's say you're doing multi-achine serving. So you're serving
multi-achine serving. So you're serving on um you know different machines uh you
on um you know different machines uh you know maybe you have a data center with
know maybe you have a data center with like 64 nodes or 128 nodes or something
like 64 nodes or 128 nodes or something like this. um every time a request comes
like this. um every time a request comes in, you want to route it to the machine
in, you want to route it to the machine that has your KV cache that has the best
that has your KV cache that has the best KV cache for you um to be accessing and
KV cache for you um to be accessing and so that you actually have cache aware
so that you actually have cache aware routing uh route it to the appropriate
routing uh route it to the appropriate place and then have the worker with the
place and then have the worker with the best uh KV cache match uh process set.
best uh KV cache match uh process set. And so
And so I love getting all my uh my serving
I love getting all my uh my serving statistics from Open Router um because
statistics from Open Router um because they have so much data and uh they cover
they have so much data and uh they cover all of the things I want to talk about,
all of the things I want to talk about, but I believe they even have
but I believe they even have a ranking of providers by cash hit rate.
a ranking of providers by cash hit rate. [laughter]
[laughter] I'm sorry mist the data the data doesn't
I'm sorry mist the data the data doesn't lie but um you can see uh mistrol has
lie but um you can see uh mistrol has the worst cache hit rate and then um you
the worst cache hit rate and then um you have other one other ones like Alibaba
have other one other ones like Alibaba cloud or dicard or silicon flow that
cloud or dicard or silicon flow that have higher cash hit rates um this is
have higher cash hit rates um this is not entirely reflective of the provider
not entirely reflective of the provider being bad or something like that it
being bad or something like that it could be just the workloads that they're
could be just the workloads that they're running but there's a number of things
running but there's a number of things that like actually factor into
that like actually factor into into this cache hit rate and um one of
into this cache hit rate and um one of them one of them is how good is the cash
them one of them is how good is the cash routing. The other one is how fast is
routing. The other one is how fast is the cash eviction. Um so the providers
the cash eviction. Um so the providers will not hold your cash for you forever.
will not hold your cash for you forever. Um they will uh you know evict your cash
Um they will uh you know evict your cash after a certain amount of time. Does
after a certain amount of time. Does anyone know how long this is for like
anyone know how long this is for like popular providers? Have you ever taken a
popular providers? Have you ever taken a look at that
look at that >> yet?
>> yet? Close to an hour.
Close to an hour. >> Close to an hour. I I think the long
>> Close to an hour. I I think the long like I'm not I'm not like super up to
like I'm not I'm not like super up to date on this, but I know anthropic used
date on this, but I know anthropic used to be five minutes. And so it's
to be five minutes. And so it's basically if you have a an active
basically if you have a an active conversation going on with them and you
conversation going on with them and you don't pause your conversation, you'll
don't pause your conversation, you'll stay in the cache. Otherwise, if you
stay in the cache. Otherwise, if you like stop the conversation, you get
like stop the conversation, you get evicted from the cache. I think you at
evicted from the cache. I think you at least have an option to go up to an hour
least have an option to go up to an hour now. Um but I don't know if you um but
now. Um but I don't know if you um but like it costs a little bit more if you
like it costs a little bit more if you go up to an hour or something. Um but
go up to an hour or something. Um but yeah, ba basically they don't want to
yeah, ba basically they don't want to keep this around because there this is a
keep this around because there this is a huge amount of memory uh that they're
huge amount of memory uh that they're keeping in memory and so they want to
keeping in memory and so they want to use it if it's working and and evict it
use it if it's working and and evict it if it's not working. So um that that's
if it's not working. So um that that's another policy that could change your
another policy that could change your cash hit rate. The bad news for us as
cash hit rate. The bad news for us as users is the pricing doesn't change no
users is the pricing doesn't change no matter how good the provider is at
matter how good the provider is at routing or um or cash eviction. So you
routing or um or cash eviction. So you uh you might be paying just because they
uh you might be paying just because they evict you uh evict you too quickly which
evict you uh evict you too quickly which seems a little bit unfair.
seems a little bit unfair. >> Um yeah
>> Um yeah >> do they use like cash layering where you
>> do they use like cash layering where you can store it on device in memory that's
can store it on device in memory that's like adjusted to device and then on this
like adjusted to device and then on this >> yeah so the that's a great question. So
>> yeah so the that's a great question. So the question was, do they use a cache
the question was, do they use a cache layering where you have like a fast
layering where you have like a fast cache that's stored in the device and
cache that's stored in the device and then uh a slower cache that's stored on
then uh a slower cache that's stored on disk or something like that? I actually
disk or something like that? I actually don't know the answer to that question.
don't know the answer to that question. That'd be a great uh like a great
That'd be a great uh like a great follow-up for us to do. Um the open
follow-up for us to do. Um the open source libraries also are probably not
source libraries also are probably not as sophisticated as the closed libraries
as sophisticated as the closed libraries because um if you look at all the people
because um if you look at all the people on open router their job is to be really
on open router their job is to be really good at serving and so you know they're
good at serving and so you know they're some of them might be using open source
some of them might be using open source libraries but they'll be building stuff
libraries but they'll be building stuff on top of them and that's kind of their
on top of them and that's kind of their you know competitive differentiation. So
you know competitive differentiation. So um like I I think
um like I I think the internal solutions that inference
the internal solutions that inference providers are likely to be you know a
providers are likely to be you know a bit better than the ones that are
bit better than the ones that are available in open source too with
available in open source too with respect to that.
respect to that. >> They usually offload to CPU from GPU.
>> They usually offload to CPU from GPU. >> They usually offload to CPU from GPU.
>> They usually offload to CPU from GPU. Yeah.
Yeah. >> Yeah. Because your GPU memory is so
>> Yeah. Because your GPU memory is so precious. So yeah. Yeah.
>> Cool. Um so uh yeah. Oh, sorry. I skipped a important part. So, what does
skipped a important part. So, what does this mean? If you're just designing a
this mean? If you're just designing a harness and you're not deploying models
harness and you're not deploying models or or anything like this, it means you
or or anything like this, it means you need to be super super careful to not
need to be super super careful to not break your cache unintentionally.
break your cache unintentionally. So, remember that your cache only works
So, remember that your cache only works if the entire prefix is exactly the
if the entire prefix is exactly the same. And so there's a bunch of things
same. And so there's a bunch of things that we've thought about
that we've thought about uh doing but we decided are a very bad
uh doing but we decided are a very bad idea because we don't want to break the
idea because we don't want to break the cache. So one thing that's completely
cache. So one thing that's completely forbidden you should not do is don't
forbidden you should not do is don't change the system message every time you
change the system message every time you uh you take a step because that means
uh you take a step because that means like no caching essentially. uh you
like no caching essentially. uh you don't have a single message that you're
don't have a single message that you're able to cache. So one thing one very
able to cache. So one thing one very logical thing that you might think of is
logical thing that you might think of is okay I want to append the current time
okay I want to append the current time and date to the system message uh so
and date to the system message uh so that the agent knows what time it is. Do
that the agent knows what time it is. Do not do this because the time and date
not do this because the time and date changes every step and so that will
changes every step and so that will break your cache. So if you do need to
break your cache. So if you do need to append it, append it to the final user
append it, append it to the final user message uh or the final uh tool call
message uh or the final uh tool call result that you get. um and uh like
result that you get. um and uh like changing your um changing your tools uh
changing your um changing your tools uh dynamically in the middle of the
dynamically in the middle of the conversation. You can do this. That's
conversation. You can do this. That's okay. Um another thing is a very logical
okay. Um another thing is a very logical thing that you might think of doing is
thing that you might think of doing is routing to a different model every time
routing to a different model every time you uh every time you take a step. So
you uh every time you take a step. So it's like this step looks like a really
it's like this step looks like a really good model for you know a really power a
good model for you know a really power a really good step for a really powerful
really good step for a really powerful model. um like uh like I want to do this
model. um like uh like I want to do this step on Fable and then I want to do the
step on Fable and then I want to do the ne next three steps on um on a cheaper
ne next three steps on um on a cheaper model to save money. But the thing is
model to save money. But the thing is you're still paying
you're still paying you're still paying the you know 10x
you're still paying the you know 10x cost for Fable the next time you use uh
cost for Fable the next time you use uh Fable. So you really need to be very uh
Fable. So you really need to be very uh frugal in the amount of switching you're
frugal in the amount of switching you're going to be doing if you want to be
going to be doing if you want to be doing switching to save cost for
doing switching to save cost for instance.
Cool. Um, so the final thing I'd like to talk
so the final thing I'd like to talk about is context compaction. Um, how
about is context compaction. Um, how many people know know about this? Use
many people know know about this? Use this in your everyday coding agent use.
this in your everyday coding agent use. How many people are really excited when
How many people are really excited when it says compacting context?
it says compacting context? [laughter]
[laughter] That's nobody good. So um the the basic
That's nobody good. So um the the basic idea behind context compaction is uh
idea behind context compaction is uh that you have uh before
that you have uh before and uh this is you know all your
and uh this is you know all your observations and actions that you might
observations and actions that you might have had. Um then after what you tend to
have had. Um then after what you tend to do is you tend to take your previous
do is you tend to take your previous context and you crush it down into just
context and you crush it down into just the essence of the previous context. Um,
the essence of the previous context. Um, and so the reason why people are
and so the reason why people are like not excited about using this, uh,
like not excited about using this, uh, perhaps obviously is if you do a bad job
perhaps obviously is if you do a bad job at this, your agent forgets things. It
at this, your agent forgets things. It starts doing something completely
starts doing something completely different and, uh, maybe deletes your
different and, uh, maybe deletes your file system.
file system. So
So um we can view compaction as essentially
um we can view compaction as essentially trying to come up with a previous
trying to come up with a previous representation where your future action
representation where your future action sequence um you take your history, you
sequence um you take your history, you compact that, you get a working state
compact that, you get a working state and you want your future action sequence
and you want your future action sequence to be the same or you know similar or
to be the same or you know similar or possibly better um if uh after
possibly better um if uh after compaction than it was before. Um
compaction than it was before. Um at the same time you also have a
at the same time you also have a constraint which your
constraint which your state needs to be bounded. So it needs
state needs to be bounded. So it needs to be small enough that you're happy to
to be small enough that you're happy to continue work.
continue work. Um so if we look at what survives uh
Um so if we look at what survives uh compaction um there's different ways of
compaction um there's different ways of doing this. I'm going to cover the
doing this. I'm going to cover the different ways that people do this, but
different ways that people do this, but a common strategy is to take some
a common strategy is to take some anchors and these can be the very first
anchors and these can be the very first um like the very first things the user
um like the very first things the user said when they started the session for
said when they started the session for instance. Um,
instance. Um, so, uh, one of the answers to the things
so, uh, one of the answers to the things that I heard agents forget when I asked
that I heard agents forget when I asked the question, what do agents forget was
the question, what do agents forget was sometimes they forget the things at the
sometimes they forget the things at the very beginning of the session? And
very beginning of the session? And that actually might be a design bug in
that actually might be a design bug in the agent harness that you're using. Um,
the agent harness that you're using. Um, because uh, some good agent harnesses
because uh, some good agent harnesses uh, like kind of intentionally avoid
uh, like kind of intentionally avoid deleting the stuff at the very beginning
deleting the stuff at the very beginning of the session because they think it's
of the session because they think it's more important. Um, but it could also
more important. Um, but it could also be, you know, impossible to avoid
be, you know, impossible to avoid depending on the situation. Um, also you
depending on the situation. Um, also you want the stuff in the middle that's
want the stuff in the middle that's encoded and put back into the context.
encoded and put back into the context. And then the recent tail is often kept
And then the recent tail is often kept around. So often people will keep around
around. So often people will keep around the the most recent actions.
the the most recent actions. Separately from this, I don't see this a
Separately from this, I don't see this a whole lot, but um, you can also add the
whole lot, but um, you can also add the evidence to an evidence store. Actually,
evidence to an evidence store. Actually, no, sorry. I I'll correct this. Um, the
no, sorry. I I'll correct this. Um, the evidence is typically added to an
evidence is typically added to an evidence store. Um, and at the very
evidence store. Um, and at the very least, if you're using a CLI coding
least, if you're using a CLI coding agent, usually your full history is
agent, usually your full history is saved on disk somewhere. And so, if you
saved on disk somewhere. And so, if you know where on disk, your coding agent
know where on disk, your coding agent has saved all of this history. Even if
has saved all of this history. Even if you lose stuff through compaction, you
you lose stuff through compaction, you can tell the coding agent to go back and
can tell the coding agent to go back and read the history, and it can, you know,
read the history, and it can, you know, uh, read the history for you and find
uh, read the history for you and find the the previous results. Um but there
the the previous results. Um but there there are also uh possibly more
there are also uh possibly more structured ways of doing this and so
structured ways of doing this and so then um you know other things can be
then um you know other things can be discarded.
discarded. Um so there's a few ways to decide uh
Um so there's a few ways to decide uh compaction policy. Um the first one is
compaction policy. Um the first one is the trigger and there's
the trigger and there's um
um essentially two ways of doing this. Um
essentially two ways of doing this. Um one is a token threshold. So you limit
one is a token threshold. So you limit uh the token threshold. Uh so you can
uh the token threshold. Uh so you can say I'm I'm only going to use up to 200k
say I'm I'm only going to use up to 200k tokens. Once I go over 200k tokens, I'm
tokens. Once I go over 200k tokens, I'm I'm going to compact the context.
I'm going to compact the context. Another thing is um like when you get
Another thing is um like when you get forced to do that by the provider. Um so
forced to do that by the provider. Um so that's kind of like a hard limit on the
that's kind of like a hard limit on the number of tokens you can have. Um
number of tokens you can have. Um finally, you can also have a manual
finally, you can also have a manual request. And so uh a lot of uh kind of
request. And so uh a lot of uh kind of coding agent toolkits for instance have
coding agent toolkits for instance have a slashcompact
a slashcompact uh like command that you can use to
uh like command that you can use to compact the context.
Um then based on that uh you'll select you might protect the beginning and keep
you might protect the beginning and keep the recent tail and compact the older
the recent tail and compact the older region. Um replace it with a summary. Um
region. Um replace it with a summary. Um that summary can be a structured
that summary can be a structured summary. So sometimes uh they require a
summary. So sometimes uh they require a tool call uh that says this and this and
tool call uh that says this and this and this and this must be in the compaction
this and this must be in the compaction summary. Sometimes it's just free text.
summary. Sometimes it's just free text. Um there's also uh
Um there's also uh I think this is only open AI uh
I think this is only open AI uh possibly. But basically they um they
possibly. But basically they um they compact into
compact into something encrypted uh that you cannot
something encrypted uh that you cannot read. So you can't see how they're
read. So you can't see how they're compacting because they don't want you
compacting because they don't want you to steal their uh their precious
to steal their uh their precious compaction algorithm. Uh so uh so
compaction algorithm. Uh so uh so there's that.
there's that. Um and then uh yeah, you can you can
Um and then uh yeah, you can you can keep on on working on that.
keep on on working on that. Um
Um so
so one of the risks here is uh sometimes
one of the risks here is uh sometimes you can compact over and over and over
you can compact over and over and over again and the first time it works uh but
again and the first time it works uh but as you walk through more um you uh you
as you walk through more um you uh you end up losing more and more. So again
end up losing more and more. So again this is one of the reasons why people
this is one of the reasons why people don't like compaction because it can
don't like compaction because it can cause the agent to go off the rails.
cause the agent to go off the rails. Um so uh ba basically the way we
Um so uh ba basically the way we evaluate this is typically in a holistic
evaluate this is typically in a holistic state. So you can vary the compaction
state. So you can vary the compaction algorithm and evaluate it against
algorithm and evaluate it against whatever benchmarks you're evaluating
whatever benchmarks you're evaluating against. I would like to warn you uh
against. I would like to warn you uh about this. I have a a kind of like
about this. I have a a kind of like story from when we were first developing
story from when we were first developing open hands which is um we actually I
open hands which is um we actually I think made one of the first like
think made one of the first like production grade uh compaction
production grade uh compaction algorithms. We called it compression
algorithms. We called it compression then um and we evaluated it against
then um and we evaluated it against bbench which is a very common you know
bbench which is a very common you know benchmark for for coding agents and we
benchmark for for coding agents and we worked pretty hard on it like as a
worked pretty hard on it like as a research project for about a month or
research project for about a month or something like that and we were like we
something like that and we were like we found this great compaction strategy. It
found this great compaction strategy. It doesn't reduce our score at all. it's
doesn't reduce our score at all. it's saving us a lot of tokens. And then we
saving us a lot of tokens. And then we actually tried it in our um we tried it
actually tried it in our um we tried it in our our system and it made these
in our our system and it made these really silly mistakes like um sending a
really silly mistakes like um sending a pull request every time it compacted. So
pull request every time it compacted. So it forgot that it had sent a pull
it forgot that it had sent a pull request to GitHub. And so uh you know we
request to GitHub. And so uh you know we would get five pull requests for the
would get five pull requests for the same functionality because it had
same functionality because it had forgotten. Um or you know it would
forgotten. Um or you know it would forget
forget user instructions that were sent in the
user instructions that were sent in the middle of the conversation because we
middle of the conversation because we had only evaluated on single turn
had only evaluated on single turn conversations that had a single user
conversations that had a single user message and we were compacting away the
message and we were compacting away the multiple user messages. So it's not just
multiple user messages. So it's not just good enough to benchmark uh unless you
good enough to benchmark uh unless you have really really robust benchmarks
have really really robust benchmarks that represent every use case. You kind
that represent every use case. You kind of need to test them in the wild as
of need to test them in the wild as well.
well. Cool. Um so we're we're getting close to
Cool. Um so we're we're getting close to time. Uh but yeah, basically uh what I
time. Uh but yeah, basically uh what I covered today is uh you know agent loops
covered today is uh you know agent loops grow very quickly. Uh we have a lot of
grow very quickly. Uh we have a lot of inference challenges in doing so. uh we
inference challenges in doing so. uh we can handle uh efficiency problems
can handle uh efficiency problems through architectures and um and caching
through architectures and um and caching and uh compaction is kind of the way we
and uh compaction is kind of the way we handle this uh once we expand beyond the
handle this uh once we expand beyond the level that we can handle. So um that's
level that we can handle. So um that's all I have. Uh if there is any questions
all I have. Uh if there is any questions happy to happy to cover them and next
happy to happy to cover them and next time we're going to be talking about
time we're going to be talking about skills and memory. So this is like even
skills and memory. So this is like even longer context over your entire uh your
longer context over your entire uh your entire time. Um, are there any questions
entire time. Um, are there any questions before we all uh all leave or
before we all uh all leave or >> Yeah.
>> Yeah, great question. Um, the question was, do we consider sub agents as a way
was, do we consider sub agents as a way to manage context? And yes, but we're
to manage context? And yes, but we're going to talk about sub aents later, so
going to talk about sub aents later, so I didn't cover them this time. Yeah.